<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Exalted Diotrephes reprehended, or, The spirit of error and envy in William Rogers against the truth and many of the antient and faithful Friends thereof manifested in his late monstrous birth or, work of darkness, (viz.), his false and scandalous book, intituled, The Christian Quaker-distinguished, &amp;c. ...</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 98 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60699</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4390</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4219</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12018976</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12018976</idno>
            <idno type="VID">52601</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60699)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 52601)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 878:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Exalted Diotrephes reprehended, or, The spirit of error and envy in William Rogers against the truth and many of the antient and faithful Friends thereof manifested in his late monstrous birth or, work of darkness, (viz.), his false and scandalous book, intituled, The Christian Quaker-distinguished, &amp;c. ...</title>
                  <author>Snead, Richard, d. 1711.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Bringhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed: Richard Snead, Charles Harford, Richard Vickris, Charles Jones.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Rogers, William, d. ca. 1709. --  Christian-Quaker distinguished from the apostate &amp; innovator.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:52601:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:52601:1"/>
            <p>AN <hi>Exalted Diotrephes</hi> REPREHENDED, Or the Spirit of Error and Envy IN <hi>William Rogers</hi> againſt the <hi>TRUTH</hi> And many of the Antient and Faithful <hi>Friends</hi> thereof, Manifeſted in his late Monſtrous <hi>Birth,</hi> or <hi>Work of Darkneſs, <hi>(viz.)</hi>
               </hi> his Falſe and Scandalous Book, Intituled, <hi>The Chriſtian Quaker-Diſtinguiſhed,</hi> &amp;c. Wherein he hath diſcovered himſelf to be an <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate,</hi> and not the <hi>True Chriſtian Quaker;</hi> but as one driven out from the Preſence of the <hi>Lord,</hi> and Unity with His Choſen People.</p>
            <p>Alſo a Compariſon between his ſaid <hi>Book,</hi> and many <hi>Exhortations</hi> and <hi>Reproofs,</hi> Contained in an <hi>Epiſtle,</hi> given forth under his Hand againſt that Spirit, and work of Diviſion, he is now fallen under; whereby his Apoſtacy, Self Contradiction, and Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion may appear.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To be diſperſed only among</hi> Friends, <hi>unleſs his Book is made more Publick.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Out of thy own Mouth will I Judge thee, thou Wicked Servant, <bibl>
                  <hi>Luk. 19.22.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>But Evil Men and Seducers ſhall Wax worſe and worſe, Deceiving and being Deceived, <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Tim. 3.13, 14.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>But continue thou in the things which thou haſt Learned, and been Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of, knowing of whom thou haſt Learned them, <bibl>
                  <hi>verſ. 14.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>In</hi> verſ. <hi>9, 10.</hi>
               </bibl> But <hi>Diotrephes,</hi> who Loveth to have the Preheminence, prating againſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s with malicious Words, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Bringhurſt,</hi> Printer and Stationer, at the Sign of the <hi>Book</hi> in <hi>Grace-Church-Street.</hi> 1681.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="note">
            <pb facs="tcp:52601:2"/>
            <p>
               <hi>LEt it not ſeem ſtrange to any,</hi> As though ſome new thing had happened unto <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s, <hi>that We have Occaſion thus publickly to Appear againſt One that hath made Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the</hi> Truth <hi>with Us, but is gone out from Us; according to that of 1</hi> John <hi>4.2. &amp; 1.9.</hi> They went out from <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s, but they were not of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s; for if they had been of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s, they would no doubt have Continued with <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s: But they went out, that they might be made Manifeſt, that they were not all of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:52601:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>AMongſt the many <hi>Exerciſes</hi> and <hi>Perils,</hi> the Lords People in this Age, as in all Ages have met with, they have not been un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acquainted with Perils by <hi>Falſe Brethren,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to what the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> Teſtified, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.30. <hi>Alſo of your own ſelves, ſhall Men Ariſe, ſpeaking perverſe things, to draw away Diſciples after them;</hi> whoſe Qualifications are at Large ſpoken of by the ſaid Apoſtle, in his Second Epiſtle to <hi>Timothy,</hi> and Third, <hi>(viz.) Without natural Affection, Truce-Breakers, falſe Accuſers, Incontinent, fierce Deſpiſers of thoſe that are Good, Traitors, Heady, High-Minded,</hi> &amp;c. as the certain Fruits, by which they ſhould be known.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:52601:3"/>
            <p>To the Great Exerciſe, Grief, and Sorrow of the Faithful, there hath not been wanting divers of the like Inſtances of ſuch Men, who ſince we have been a People, have Ariſen from amongſt our ſelves (as this Man <hi>William Rogers</hi> now doth) under the <hi>Profeſſion of the Truth, to oppoſe and gain-ſay the Bleſſed Order and Government thereof,</hi> whereby the looſe Converſations of the Wicked are Reſtrained or Judged, and the <hi>Truth</hi> cleared from the Reproach thereof. And theſe have not been without the like ſpecious pretences with <hi>William Rogers,</hi> as ſtanding up for the <hi>Ancient Teſtimony,</hi> and <hi>Principle of the Light,</hi> and againſt <hi>Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, ſetting up Mans Preſcriptions, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, Innovations, Perſecutions,</hi> &amp;c. but their Fruits withering: And their End hath made them Manifeſt, as this Mans alſo doth, and will do, to be the Men Apoſtatized them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, Led, and Acted by a Spirit that would open a Gap, and break down the Hedge, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Man may do as he Liſt, whilſt under the
<pb facs="tcp:52601:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>Profeſſion of the ſame Truth, without being cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to Account, and dealt with in a Goſpel-Church-Order for it.</p>
            <p>This ſmall Treatiſe is not Intended for a full Anſwer to <hi>William Rogers</hi>'s Voluminous Book, which requires a conſiderable time for Inſpection into divers Matters and Papers; for ſuch a Reply to trace him in all his <hi>Falſe Inſinuations, grievous Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſions, and notorious falſe Charges</hi> of many Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Men, and Faithful and Eminent Labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers in the Work of the Goſpel amongſt Us, already Manifeſt to Us by their <hi>Anſwers</hi> and <hi>Certificates</hi> in Writing; wherein they have Largely Vindicated their Innocency, in moſt, if not all thoſe things relating to matter of Fact, alledged againſt them, eſpecially <hi>G. F.</hi> and have cauſed Copies thereof to be Delivered to <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Rogers</hi> many Months ſince, and long before his Book was in the Preſs: Such more full An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer more publickly to be made, we Refer to ſome other Hand or Hands, who are Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently concerned to do it. In the mean time,
<pb facs="tcp:52601:4"/>we thought it not Amiſs, to give the Reader ſome ſhort diſcovery of the <hi>Subject,</hi> and <hi>Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> of the Differences <hi>William Rogers</hi> Writeth about; and of <hi>His Work</hi> in General; and that by Comparing his former Exhortations and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofs, with his late Printed Book, and Beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour amongſt Us; the <hi>Reader</hi> may have ſome Taſte of his Spirit of <hi>Errour and Envy,</hi> and be cautioned in himſelf thereby, how he gives Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit to his many, and falſe Accuſations againſt the Innocent.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:52601:4"/>
            <head>An Exalted <hi>Diotrephes</hi> Reprehended.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>WHen the Unclean Spirit is gone out of a Man, he walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth through dry Places ſeeking Reſt, and finding none.</p>
                  <p>Then he ſaith, I will Return into mine Houſe, from whence I came out; and when he is come, he findeth it Swept and Garniſht.</p>
                  <p>Then Goeth he, and taketh with himſelf Seven other Spirits, more Wicked than himſelf, and they Enter in, and Dwell there; and the laſt State of that Man is worſe than the firſt, even ſo ſhall it be to this Wicked Generation,</p>
               </q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Mat. 12. verſ. 43, 44, 45.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THat this is the Caſe of this miſerable Man <hi>William Rogers,</hi> manifeſted by his late Fruits, is paſt doubt with us, whom, through <hi>Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>watchfulneſs, Diſobedience,</hi> and <hi>Rebellion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst God</hi> (which is as the Sin of <hi>Witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft</hi>) the unclean Spirit and Adverſary of Mans Soul, the old <hi>Accuſer of the Brethren,</hi> hath thus Entred, and Exalted upon the Pinnacle of his own conceited Abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; and having now the Rule in him, and over him, makes War through him, againſt the Lamb and His fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers; and having fitted him for his Service, now ſets him about that which hath been all along his Work <hi>(viz.)</hi> To Reproach the faithful People of God, the whole Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, and the good Order and Government of the Truth, which the Lord hath brought forth amongſt them (as that which ſtriketh at the downfal of his Kingdom)
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:52601:5"/>with many falſe and opprobrious Accuſations, as of being <hi>Apoſtatized,</hi> and Guilty of <hi>Impoſition, Perſecution, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novation, Gentilian-Lordſhip, Blind Obedience,</hi> &amp;c. whereby <hi>William Rogers</hi> hath not only Rankt himſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong a Number of thoſe <hi>Apoſtates,</hi> who from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in a Spirit of Enmity and Prejudice have riſen up like <hi>Core</hi> (ſaying) <hi>You take too much upon you,</hi> againſt the <hi>Heavenly Care and Order</hi> of ſuch as truely Fear and Love <hi>God,</hi> and in whom, as he himſelf hath confeſſed, <hi>God hath opened Councel for that End</hi> (viz.) <hi>To be as Helps and Governments in the Church, which are not to be Deſpiſed, being in Subjection to Chriſt, the one Head, and Law-giver.</hi> But as may appear in the following Epiſtle, with this Aggravation, <hi>That which he formerly Approved and Exhorted to, he is now found ſmiting againſt, and what he then ſeverely detested and reproved in others, He is now found heinouſly Guilty of himſelf</hi> (viz) of Repreſenting ſuch as <hi>Aiming at other Ends and Intereſts, in ſuch their Religious Care, and Heavenly Order and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, than Chriſt's Intereſt and Government over All;</hi> whereby out of his own Mouth he is Condemned.</p>
            <p>And now for as much as he hath ſo publickly, and injuriouſly appeared in his late Book, to the great Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal of our Profeſſion, as an open Enemy to the Truth, we are concerned for the Honour of the Lord's Name, which is dear unto us, publickly to make him manifeſt <hi>(A work otherwiſe not pleaſing to Us)</hi> that he may proceed no further, but that his Folly may appear to all Men, and that the <hi>Ignominy and Reproach,</hi> he hath as much as in him lieth, brought upon the Lords People, and faithful Labourers, and their Holy Profeſſion, may be Rouled and Waſhed away.</p>
            <p>But before we proceed to make <hi>William Rogers</hi> mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt by his late Fruits among us, we think it requiſite to give ſome ſhort Account of the Subject, Occaſion,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:52601:5"/>and preſent ſtate of the Diviſions mentioned in his Book, and how <hi>William Rogers</hi> is concerned therein.</p>
            <p>Many of the antient and faithful Brethren of the Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern parts, as we are credibly informed, being under an Exerciſe in their Spirits, by reaſon of the Unfaithfulneſs of ſome that walk amongſt them, with Reſpect to divers things, amongſt whom <hi>J. S. J. W.</hi> &amp;c. were Intereſted, they had a godly care upon their Spirits, to make a nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row ſearch and inſpection thereinto, which the Guilty could not bear, but ſet themſelves to oppoſe their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings; by which means a great difference aroſe: ſo that the Friends who were zealous againſt ſuch as were Back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſliding from the Truth, and its Heavenly way and Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, remained ſome time under a burthen and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe becauſe thereof. At length, as we are credibly infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, the Friends of the Quarterly Meeting at <hi>Kendal,</hi> made known their Exerciſe to divers other Brethren, deſiring a meeting with <hi>J. S.</hi> and <hi>J. W.</hi> before them, in order to the compoſing the Difference, which was Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected by them. However, thoſe Friends and Brethren ſent to them again, and alſo ſome of them went to them, and appointed a Meeting, near the place where they were, deſiring them to come, but they would not, as holding themſelves not obliged to ſubmit to them in that caſe, and leaving things under this ſtate of Diſ-reconciliation, came into the <hi>South,</hi> making their complaints, and ſpread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their differences, particularly amongſt us at <hi>Briſtol,</hi> where they met with ſome that adhered to them, ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened them, and ſet them up, too forwardly <hi>Eſpouſing the Cauſe upon the alone hearing of their Complaints againſt the Friends of the other Party,</hi> who were far diſtant from us; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the reſt, <hi>William Rogers</hi> was an early Proſelite, and ſo great a Devotee to theſe mens Intereſt, that he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtriouſly laboured to Proſelite others there-unto, upon
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:52601:6"/>the Credit of his pretended knowledge of the ground of thoſe Differences: what an evil Inſtrument this man was, from the beginning thereof, in this City and elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, is not eaſily to be Related, how he forſtering up <hi>J. S.</hi> and <hi>J. W.</hi> laboured to ſtave off the early endeavours and expedients for reconciliation, as being not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuited to his mind, who was now become as a <hi>Maſter of this Faction,</hi> with which ſome of this City were like to be led aſide, whoſe Souls the Lord in his Mercy hath Reſcued out of the Snare.</p>
            <p>The Intelligence of thoſe Differences, ſpreading through divers Parts of the Nation, eſpecially where <hi>J. S.</hi> and <hi>J. W.</hi> Travelled and Reſorted; a Concern under the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of the evil conſequences thereof, came upon ſome Antient Brethren, to endeavour a ſpeedy ſtop there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, moved for a new Hearing, which at length was agreed to on all hands. Accordingly a meeting was appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and held at <hi>Drawel</hi> in <hi>York-ſhire, Anno</hi> 1676. to which reſorted ſeveral of the Ancient Friends and Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, leaving all Occaſions and Relations in love to God, and earneſt deſires for the preſervation of the <hi>Church's Peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After their great Travel, and tender Endeavours, then for Reconciliation and Peace, <hi>J. S.</hi> and <hi>J. W.</hi> being bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into ſome Degree of Submiſſion, at length produce a Paper Containing a <hi>Condemnation againſt themſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It may not be amiſs here to Relate out of <hi>W. R.</hi> his Narrative, the Character he hath given of the <hi>Temper</hi> and <hi>Frame</hi> of the Spirits of thoſe Brethren at the Mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting at <hi>Drawel,</hi> when they gave forth their Sence, and Account, concerning the Difference relating to <hi>J. S.</hi> and <hi>J. W.</hi> which doth not a little confirm the Integrity and Soundneſs of it, being from the Pen of ſo great an Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſer and Villifier, as he hath Manifeſted himſelf to be.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:52601:6"/>
            <p>The words of <hi>W. Rogers</hi> on the aforeſaid account are, that,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In all friends there appeared as far as I could per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, a ſpirit inclined to peace and unity in the Cruth, many hearts being bowed down, in the earneſt deſires of their ſouls breathing unto God, and that in great Zeal, and ſincerity for the gathering them into nearer Vnion and fellowſhip with their brethren therein.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, in his account of the Fourth days Travel, he ſaith as follows.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The matter ſo gone through, and ended, the brethren waited, and great was the exerciſe that was upon their ſpirits, for a very conſiderable time; after ſome ſilence the brethren choſen at London, and many other Friends, that were not of the ſix laſt choſen, ſpoke their ſenſe and Iudgment upon the whole matter, not only relating to the fact before them, but alſo to that ſpirit, which according to their inward ſenſe, cauſed a ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to this effect:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That they</hi> (viz.) [I. S. <hi>and</hi>] I. W. <hi>had not kept in V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity with their brethren, as they ought to have done; but had let in jealouſies, doubts and ſcruples, whereby they had given way to a ſpirit of diviſion and ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; which ſpirit they did condemn and judge, yet ſo as there appeared amongſt the brethren, a Travelling Love and Life beyond what I can now declare, that they might not be cut off from them, but brought into perfect Vnity with them: ſo that at length, the two ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed brethren, being, as I was perfectly ſenſible, ready to condeſcend to their brethren, therein, ſo far as their underſtandings were opened, brought forth this Inſuing Paper of ſatisfaction to their Travelling brethren, and the Churches of Chriſt.</hi> Thus far <hi>R. W.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:52601:7"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Here follows their Paper of Condemnation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVE are ſenſible, that in the hour of Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, that hath appeared through us, which hath given an occaſion of offence to the Churches of God, unto whom the knowledge of the Northern differences hath come, and ſince the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſenſe of our brethren, who we are ſenſible, have a Travel on their ſpirits, for preſervation of peace and Vnity in the Church of God, concerning us is ſuch, That Iealouſies have entred us, and that we have been at ſomtimes exerciſed in things, tending to oppoſe Friends in the practice of thoſe things, that they teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, are commendable in the Church of God; we are ſorry that any weakneſs ſhould appear in us to give occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for ſuch offence, and as</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">How comes it to paſs, that there is now <hi>nothing</hi> in all this, and that it is no better than a <hi>Rattle to pleaſe Children?</hi> is not this manifeſt <hi>deceit</hi> and <hi>hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie?</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſatisfaction to our brethren, and the Church of God in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, we do from the very bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of our hearts condemn that ſpirit, whether it hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in us or any, that hath given offence to the Church of God in general, or that oppoſe the order of the Goſpel, or any faithful Brethren in the practice of thoſe things they believe are their Duty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This paper being ſent to ſome Friends in divers parts of the Nation, for the ſatisfaction of ſuch to whom-the knowledge of the differences had come; the end for which it was given forth <hi>J. S.</hi> and <hi>J. VV.</hi> were offended at it, ſet themſelves to extenuate (or take off) the weight of it; not owning it according to the common acceptation of <hi>A condemnation of themſelves therein;</hi> confeſſing, <hi>they owned the Paper, but in another ſence, than againſt themſelves.</hi> Notwithſtanding, what it plainly imports, and they
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:52601:7"/>knew the Brethren took it for; and <hi>William Rogers,</hi> who confeſſed he drew it for <hi>J. S.</hi> and <hi>J. W.</hi> Reported, <hi>there was nothing in it;</hi> and that the <hi>moſt innocent man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us might own it, and never hurt himſelf;</hi> and <hi>that it was no better than a Rattle to pleaſe Children:</hi> implying, thoſe Friends and Brethren Aſſembled at <hi>Drawel,</hi> he hath, as before Recited out of his own Narative, given ſuch a <hi>Character</hi> of: and theſe things we have proved al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready by ſufficient Witneſſes, out of his own mouth, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of bringing forth Fruits of <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Humiliation,</hi> the ſaid <hi>J. S.</hi> and <hi>J. W.</hi> having dealt thus un-ſincerely with the Brethren, began a new Quarrel with them that were concerned in the hearing and declaring the judgment of the Spirit of Truth, at <hi>Drawel,</hi> concerning the differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> calling their Account, <hi>a lying Narrative,</hi> and charging them with doing wickedly by them, both by word and writing; <hi>W. R.</hi> alſo joining with them, who by this time began to be deſperate, and warmly to engage in <hi>their Quarrel;</hi> and in defence of their pretended <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency,</hi> they ſet themſelves to oppoſe and Exclaim againſt the proceedings of the Brethren at <hi>Drawel-Meeting,</hi> with many opprobrious terms, in perfect contraries to the <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter W. R.</hi> had before given thereof; all which things have been made appear at large. And inſtead of break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up their ſeparate-Meeting, or clearing themſelves of them (which is a publick Enſign of Diviſion; and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to the Truth) and inſtead of making void their Subſcription, tending to a ſeparation, both are continued with <hi>J. S.</hi> and <hi>J. W</hi>'s names thereto, whereby ſome have been encouraged in the Diviſions: and ſo far have they made void (as to themſelves) the benefit of all the Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions of that Meeting at <hi>Drawel.</hi> And now becauſe the Friends of Truth, cannot be at <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Unity</hi> with them in their work of <hi>Separation</hi> and <hi>Diviſion;</hi> but keep the Spirit of ſound judgment upon that dividing Spirit,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:52601:8"/>and are at a diſtance from them, until they Repent, and be Reconciled, therefore are they diſquieted.</p>
            <p>And as for <hi>William Rogers</hi> their furious Warrier, and whom they have permitted to fight their Battells for them againſt the Lamb's followers, we have look'd upon him of late, as <hi>A Man Tormented in Spirit,</hi> under the diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointments he hath met with in his way on the one Hand,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Note,</hi> his <hi>Articles</hi> have not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Demonſtrated this to be his Deſign, but his words alſo very frequently to be what he would have accompliſhed amongſt us.</note> in not being able to Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect that <hi>Miſchief of Diviſion</hi> and <hi>Separation,</hi> which both publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and privately he hath La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured to bring to paſs in this City, about thoſe Men; and on the other Hand, finding the Cauſe of his Party, whom under pretence of Crying down Man, he hath induſtriouſly Laboured to Exalt Man or Men above, as well as againſt their Brethren, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all his Endeavours, Manifeſtly to Decline, not only in the General, but in the Conſciences of ſome from amongſt themſelves, as by divers Teſtimonies un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der many of their Hands, ſhewing how they were Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed, and Led aſide from the Antient Unity, to joyn in a Subſcription of Party with <hi>J. Story,</hi> and <hi>J. Wilkin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> may be made appear.</p>
            <p>And now, as to the utmoſt Miſchief, <hi>W. R.</hi> is able to do, he hath in the Bitterneſs and Envy of his Spirit and Power of Darkneſs, with which of late he hath been Act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Printed his moſt ſcandalous and abuſive Book, which he had long threatned to bring forth, and which is now come Abroad; and ſo Wicked, that we muſt needs ſay, though we knew the Mans lofty Spirit, and expected no other than bad from him; yet we are ſorry for his ſake, at what he hath brought forth, it being ſo <hi>Monſtrous,</hi> and <hi>Confuſed,</hi> and abundantly ſupplyed with moſt grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous <hi>Falſehood,</hi> wicked <hi>Perverſions,</hi> and <hi>Miſ-repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentations</hi> of many <hi>Faithful and Innocent Men,</hi> who tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:52601:8"/>fear God, though he hath for the moſt part omitted their <hi>Names,</hi> which we take not to be out of any Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour or Kindneſs in him towards ſuch; but rather un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Apprehenſion, that the <hi>Eminency</hi> of divers of them, together with the <hi>Credit of their Integrity</hi> in the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of perſons of all Qualities and Degrees, would have but worſted and diſſerted his Cauſe: and for as much as it is Evident to us, that the Generallity of the People called <hi>Quakers</hi> in this Nation (ſome few here and there, in ſome Countries excepted) are at Unity with thoſe Brethren in their Teſtimony againſt this <hi>Spirit</hi> and <hi>Work of Diviſion, <hi>William Rogers</hi>
               </hi> is now principally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in, and for which thoſe Brethren are ſo villified and abuſed in <hi>William Rogers</hi> his Book, we cannot but look upon ſuch his Injuries and Reproaches, to extend through them to the Body of the People called <hi>Quakers</hi> in this Nation, and their Holy Profeſſion, thereby proſtrated to the publick Ignominy and Contempt of the open and ſecret Enemies of the Truth, who may be too apt to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve what he Writeth: which being duely conſidered, let all that have the Fear of God before their Eyes, Judge whether the Man, that is Guilty of theſe things, can be rightly Eſteemed a <hi>True Chriſtian Quaker.</hi> We ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving thus given a ſhort, but true Account of the Occaſion, Subject, Proceedings, and Continuance of the preſent Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences, ſhall proceed to ſay ſomething of <hi>William Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers</hi> his late behaviour amongſt us, in this City.</p>
            <p>His Qualifications (with Reſpect to his Profeſſion) of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a <hi>True Chriſtian Quaker,</hi> is that we are concerned about; and to lay him open, as they have been plentifully Manifeſted to us, by his behaviour of late Years, amongſt us in this City, to our Great Grief and Exerciſe. Know then, that whatever <hi>William Rogers</hi> hath formerly been, or whate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver he is yet accounted to be, by any that taketh part with him, &amp; hath made him as a <hi>Head</hi> &amp; <hi>Captain</hi> in this late work
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:52601:9"/>of <hi>Strife and Diviſion,</hi> from the Antient Unity and Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip in the Truth; which the Lord through his Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Mercy, hath put a great ſtop unto, and Hedged up their Way; and is now cauſing the Rebellious Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments thereof to Wither and Blaſt, and become as <hi>Unſavo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Salt, fit for nothing, but to be trodden under the Feet of Men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for ſuch who have any Tenderneſs and Sinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty remaining in them towards the Lord and his People; ſuch the Lord hath Gathered, and is Gathering out from amongſt them; eſpecially in ſome of the <hi>Northern</hi> Parts, where this <hi>Diviſion</hi> firſt Sprang and Aroſe. We ſay, whatever <hi>William Rogers</hi> may be accounted of, by ſuch as take part with him:</p>
            <p>We, whoſe Names are Subſcribed to this ſmall Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe (being his Neighbours) have by frequent Experience, known many times to our Grief and Sorrow; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in Truth and Righteouſneſs, and in Sincerity of Heart, we declare, that he is a Man of a <hi>Heady, Willful, high-Minded, Unruly, Paſſionate,</hi> and <hi>Furious Spirit;</hi> and therefore cannot be Juſtified: <hi>For the Sway of his Fury ſhall be his Deſtruction, if he Repent not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We have known him upon frequent Occaſions, to be ſo very Extravagant with his Tongue, as well as his Pen (which we doubt not but in time will be unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niably Manifeſted in his Book) inſomuch, that his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſlanderous Aſſertions have long ſince been but of lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Credit with us: and therefore, we conclude with the Apoſtle, <hi>His Religion is vain,</hi> and whatever his talk of Religion and Chriſtianity is, it is Manifeſt to us, it conſiſts more in his <hi>Head,</hi> than in his <hi>Heart;</hi> and ſo indeed is a Stranger to the <hi>Life</hi> of it, he being alive in the contrary Nature. And truely, he hath long been a Burthen, not only to us (but as we have too much Cauſe to believe) to ſome Hundreds in this City, by his ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry rude and clamorous Behaviour, at our Mens Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:52601:9"/>as well as publick Meetings, wherein we account he hath been the chief Inſtrument of the great Diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance and Diſorder, that hath been at ſometimes therein Manifeſted; though with no ſmall Impudence he now makes mention of it in his Book, without taking <hi>Shame to himſelf;</hi> but Aſſigning to others what himſelf was Guilty of, as one chief cauſe of the preſent Publiſhing the Things contained in his Book; and having thus diligently, both ſought, cauſed, and took occaſion, he now vents the Bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſs that is in his Heart, which we believe is Nauci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and Offenſive to them that truely Fear God amongſt us.</p>
            <p>We think it not neceſſary, particularly here to Recite the many <hi>Abuſes of his laviſh Tongue,</hi> together with his <hi>Frequent, Rude, Inſolent, and Imperious Behaviour,</hi> at our Mens Meetings, as the Natural Effects of thoſe his Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications before Mentioned, wherein, and whereby he hath from time to time, Induſtriouſly Laboured to cauſe a <hi>Separation</hi> amongſt us.</p>
            <p>Neither do we think it neceſſary at preſent, to parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularize his <hi>Profane Speaking concerning the Power of God,</hi> no more than we have already done, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his <hi>Horrible unſincere Dealing with the Brethren at</hi> Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well, both proved out of his own Mouth, unleſs requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red thereto; and the Reaſon why we ſo think it not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary at Preſent, is not only for that it would Render us much the Larger, and the Credit of our Teſtimony, not ſtrictly Requiring it; but becauſe ſome of us have already, both by Word and Writing, Charged him home with divers of theſe things; ſo that he is not Ignorant of them, for which we could never have any Satisfaction, either publick or private, to this day; in ſuch Caſes of Charge againſt him, his way and manner hath been, and we Judge it is according to his Principles, <hi>To Refuſe the Submitting ſuch matters to the Hearing, Judgement, and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:52601:10"/>Determination of Friends of the Meeting, indefinitely Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in a Church-Way and Method,</hi> as is Eſtabliſh't amongſt us, for the ſtrengthning the Good, &amp; Reproof, &amp; Diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Evil and looſe Walkers. But his Manner is in ſuch Caſes to urge, <hi>The Chooſing ſo many Men on each Part,</hi> like as if the Caſe were about an Horſe or Cow; a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Method of his, to ſhelter the Head of the Tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor from the ſtroke of Righteous Judgement: A practice he hath been of late too Eminently Guilty of in our Mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, to the Grief of the Upright: <hi>For the Tranſgreſſor will be ſure to Chuſe ſuch, as are like himſelf, and of party with him, to ſtand by him to the Uttermoſt;</hi> and this ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects but Confuſion. Thus it appears, it was not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Cauſe, that <hi>William Rogers</hi> hath ſtood up ſo Zealouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for <hi>Liberty,</hi> and ſome of his Adherents <hi>againſt Month<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> and <hi>Quarterly Meetings,</hi> which called them in Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion for their back-ſliding: ſeeing they, if they ſhould ſubmit to ſuch Meetings, are likely to have their <hi>Fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Liberty</hi> Reſtrained, or to be publickly Judged, and Diſowned for it; and this is the Reaſon in the Ground and Bottom whatever contrary Pretences they make that <hi>W. R.</hi> &amp;c. are ſo diſquieted, &amp; of his Exclaiming in his book againſt the Godly <hi>Care</hi> and <hi>Zeal,</hi> of the faithful, under the black Characters of <hi>perſecution, impoſition,</hi> and the like.</p>
            <p>Theſe things conſidered, we cannot but admire at the confidence of <hi>W. Rogers</hi> in the <hi>27th.</hi> page of his Preface, wherein he ſaith, <hi>He bleſſeth God, that hath ſo preſerved him, by the Arm of his power, as that none of his Oppoſers have, ſo far as he knew, laid any thing to his charge, but for things wherein he hath acted (though miſrepreſented by them) to keep a Conſcience void of offence towards God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We whoſe names are hereunto ſubſeribed, having heard the foregoing relation of <hi>W. Rogers,</hi> his being of a <hi>heady, ſelf-will'd, unruly,</hi> and <hi>paſſionate ſpirit,</hi> of his <hi>Laviſh,</hi> and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:52601:10"/>
               <hi>abuſive tongue, rude Carriage,</hi> and <hi>behaviour</hi> in meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of late years amongſt us, do hereby certifie, that to our knowledge, the <hi>Character</hi> given of him therein is true, and that we alſo have many times, to our great grief and exerciſe, been eye, and ear witneſſes of his being notoriouſly guilty therein, to the great ſhame of his profeſſion, witneſs our hands. Dated in <hi>Briſtol,</hi> the 16th of the 6th Month, 1681.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lawrence Steel,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>John Moone,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>John Bainton,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Henry Diddicott,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Paul Moone,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Charles Jones,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sampſ. Coyſgarne,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>John Cowlinge,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>John Higgins,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>John Barnes,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>William Minor,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Peter Young,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>James Sturridg,</hi> Jun.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>William Rouch,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thomas Bayley,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Richard Philips,</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Here follows the <hi>Epiſtle</hi> before mentioned under <hi>W. Rogers</hi> &amp; <hi>Arther Eaſtmeads</hi> hands; together with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers brethren, who ſtill keep their habitations in the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the Spirit and power of God, given forth from the yearly Meeting, ſince the beginning of the <hi>Diviſions,</hi> in the North, as <hi>W. Rogers</hi> confeſſeth by the date thereof, in the ſecond page of his preface, and is a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt Reproof to that Spirit of <hi>Strif</hi> and <hi>Diviſion,</hi> then at work; as alſo a diſcovery againſt whom, and what the inſtruments thereof did then, and do ſtill oppoſe themſelves, into the miſchief of which ſpirit, and work, <hi>W. R.</hi> himſelf is of late fallen, ſo that he muſt bear his own judgement, and condemnation.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Thou art inexcuſable O man! whoſoever thou art, that judgeſt. For wherein thou judgeth another, thou condemneſt thy ſelf. For thou that judgeſt, doſt the ſame things. But we are ſure, that the judgement of God is according to Truth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst them which commit ſuch things,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Rom. 2.1.28.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:52601:11"/>
            <p>The Epiſtle, with the following Marginal obſervations, is here commended to the Conſcience of the impartia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> reader.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>London</hi> 
                        <date>the 26th 3d month, 1673.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <salute>Dear Friends and Brethren,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THe Lord our God having by his Eternal Power, raiſed up, and preſerved many faithful, and living Witneſſes of his bleſſed Truth, until this Day; both for the Converſion of many from Darkneſs to Light, and for the building up, Eſtabliſhment and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort therein by his own Living Word of Life and Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation. And having alſo ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally Bleſſed<note n="a" place="margin">This was at the yearly, or general Meeting; which Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, was then Approved by <hi>W. R.</hi> but now Smitten at by <hi>W. R.</hi> and the Members thereof, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of an uncertain Number of uncertain qualified Perſons <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 7. and yet in the ſame page, undertakes to Aſſign ſome of the following Qualifications, viz. <hi>Falſe Accuſers, Men-pleaſers, and many of them Lovers of Prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence, and time Servers, that take that as an opportunity to appear unto others, that which they are not in themſelves; and do take upon them, to call themſelves a general Meeting.</hi> See his Confuſion, and Self-contradiction, both in word and practice.</note> this precious Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of our aſſembling to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, with his glorious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, power and Majeſty, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt amongſt us, which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny were, and are Eye witneſſes of, and in the unſpeakable ſenſe thereof, many have been as melted, and their hearts ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly broken, and their ſouls overcome, and deeply affected with Gods unſpeakable goodneſs and power, love and life, ſo plentifully ſhed abroad amongſt us, and in our hearts, in the ſenſe whereof our hearts are open, and affected towards you all, even in the ſame dear, and tender love and life, that is abundantly ſhed forth unto us, and from which our ſalutation is to all our dear Friends, brethren, and Siſters, in this, and other nations: having the General State of the Churches, and people of God o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened unto us, with a tender care upon our hearts,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:52601:11"/>and breathing of our ſouls, that they all may grow, proſper, and be preſerved in <hi>Unity, Peace,</hi> and <hi>good or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> that divine life and vertue may Reign, and abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly flow over and through all, to the Repleniſhment, and unſpeakable comfort, that you may keep out the Enemy in all his appearances, that would make <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions,</hi> and <hi>diſturbances</hi> in the Churches; for at this time the Enemie is buſie, and ſecretly at work for that end, to make<note n="b" place="margin">
                        <hi>Note,</hi> the end and occaſion of this Epiſtle, againſt the Rents and Diviſions then on Foot: and now Eſpouſed by <hi>William Rogers,</hi> to the Gratifying the Enemy, and bringing the open Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers, and Adverſaries of Truth over us, formerly judged, but now practiſed by <hi>Willam Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers,</hi> witneſs his whole Book, made publick to the view of the World.</note> 
                     <hi>rents,</hi> endeavouring thereby to bring the open oppoſers, and adverſaries of Truth over; it is that ſtrife, &amp; diviſion may be ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red amongſt our ſelves, that they deſire and watch for; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore where any are inſtruments thereof, they ſerve not the Lord Ieſus Chriſt: but the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy.<note n="c" place="margin">
                        <hi>Mark,</hi> the very Character of <hi>William Rogers</hi> his Work and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and his Judgment againſt all ſuch as are Guilty of theſe things, which now includes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in chief, Witneſs not only his Offence againſt ſuch like Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortations, as excluding of Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies, and having an Eye to the Brethren, <hi>Preface, p.</hi> 6. but alſo his own evil Surmizes, and hard Speeches in this Book, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt many of theſe very Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, with whom he joyned in the Epiſtle; and many other faithful Labourers in the Lord's Work, though moſt of them are not particularly Nominated, whom he terms Up ſtarts, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novaters, Adherents to <hi>G. F. pag.</hi> 3. of his Preface; Inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting moſt grievous and faiſe Charges againſt them, as the main Deſign of his Book, ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring them <hi>Apoſtates, falſe Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers, Impoſers, Perſecutors, Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſing Gentilian Lordſhip, blind Obedience,</hi> Setting up an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>Directory, Orders, Innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Preſcriptions, Decrees,</hi> and what not; ſeeking thereby to Undermine, and to beget a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſteem, and ſlight of their Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony. See how this Man is now found in the very Practice of thoſe things he once Condemn'd; whereby, out of his own Mouth he is Judged; being like the Dog, returned to the Vomit; and the Sow that was Waſhed, to her Wallowing in the Mire.</note> They that make divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and cauſe offences, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Goſpel, and that ſeek to ſow diſcord amongſt bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, are not only to be mark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but the Lord will make them manifeſt, and his power will bring them under, and debaſe them, as it hath done (and will do) that ſpirit that is guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of jealouſies, Evil-ſurmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, whiſperings, and hard ſpeeches againſt the brethren, and faithful. Labourers in the Lords work; it is the accuſer of the brethren that ſtrikes at their Teſtimony, and ſeeks to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermine
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:52601:12"/>to beget a diſeſteem and ſlight of them in it, which ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary muſt be watch't againſt, and forever caſt down and out: and we are aſſured from the Lord, that all ſowers of diſcord, accuſers of the faithful brethren, ſlighters and undervaluers of their Teſtimony and gifts, ſelf-ſeekers, Whiſperers, Back-bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and all ſelf-willed and ſelf-exalted ſpirits, God will abaſe them, his eternal power will work them under, and all that which offends, ſhall be removed, Gods pure power is at work, refining, throughly purging his floor, and ſanctifying his Church and people, that there may be no rent, nor ſchiſm; but that the Lord may be one, and his name one, amongſt us; and bleſſed are you, that keep to your firſt love, and retain your integrity to the end.<note n="d" place="margin">Had <hi>William Rogers</hi> been of this Spirit, and continued, we had never ſeen his contrary Work of Darkneſs and Confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but this he is far from; now having approved himſelf an ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Enemy, Villifier, and Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſer of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Rule and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment in his Members; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch, that the very Term it ſelf <hi>(viz.)</hi> Church-Government is become an Offence unto him, as may appear in Divers parts of his Book, particularly <hi>Pag.</hi> 45. of <hi>part the Firſt.</hi>
                     </note> Oh, dear friends and brethren, watch in the light a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all the enemies wiles, and pray for the peace of Ieruſalem, that ſhe may be ſeen in her beauty and ſplendor, or as a City without breaches, that peace may remain within her walls, and proſperity within her pallaces: Oh! let it be the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral care of all our brethren, to whom the Lord hath committed an overſight in the Churches, to keep things quiet, and in good order by the power and wiſdom of God, who is not the Author of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, but of peace; and that the publick affairs of Truth
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:52601:12"/>be managed, and carried on in the ſame power and wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, which is pure, and peaceable that all in Humility may ſubmit to Chriſts Rule and Government in a ſpirit of meekneſs &amp; condeſcenſion; keep out all roughneſs, harſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, one towards another, and all ſelf rule, and domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that is not of the life, but in the will of the fleſh, and let all this be kept down for ever, and no ſtrange fire be kindled among you, nor in your meetings: and elders, and Overſeers, muſt not be<note n="e" place="margin">This is the very Temper and Spirit he is fallen under, as is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready Obſerved at Large.</note> ſelf willed, nor ſoon angry, nor given to haſte or paſſion, nor any ſhortneſs or britleneſs; for ſuch keep not in a ſound mind, nor in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning, either of true judgment or mercy, which are both to be exerciſed, among you, as the ſpirit of life o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peneth to you the conditions and ſtates, to which they properly belong; for as all looſeneſs, diſorderly walking, and ſcandalous converſations and practices, muſt be ſeverely reproved, and judged out, eſpecially amongſt them that are convinced of the precious Truth, and the guilty to bear their own judgment, and burthen; ſo likewiſe mercy and forgiveneſs, muſt be extended to ſuch as having been over-taken with a fault, comes to feel a true tenderneſs in their hearts through judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and to receive counſel that they may be preſerved in fear and watchfulneſs: and let not Iudgments, and Teſtimonies againſt miſcarriages and offences be made<note n="f" place="margin">If the Matters alledged in <hi>W. R.</hi> his Book againſt <hi>G. F.</hi> and others by Name, were true, How doth it agree with this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation, in making of them ſo publick as he hath done? See how he condemns that in others, which he alloweth in himſelf.</note> more publick, than the miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages are, to harden thoſe that miſcarry, and give the adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Truth advantage to throw dirt upon friends; but be careful and tender for the truth and friends in that mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and endeavour to ſave the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:52601:13"/>ſouls even of thoſe that are tempted, and drawn aſide: as alſo that private differences that may happen amongſt any friends or brethren, be ended by ſome few in the wiſdom and counſel of God, with as much pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacy as may be, without troubling or diſturbing the publick meetings, or Churches with them, and without publick reflections upon perſons, where the difference or offence on either hand, is not notorious or publickly ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, but beſt to be ended privately, both for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of them who are concerned therein, and the preventing of ſuch occaſions, as may either ſtumble the weak, cauſe confuſion, or give the world occaſion to<note n="g" place="margin">It's a very little matter what becomes of the Honour of <hi>Truth,</hi> and the Holy Profeſſion thereof, with <hi>W. R.</hi> now, who hath ſet himſelf in defiance of the Friends thereof, under the Notion of Apoſtates and Innovators.</note> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach friends and Truth. And friends, we do deſire that all differences may be ended, in the ſeveral Counties, where they do ariſe; and that the honour of God, and the peace of the Church, may be minded both by thoſe who cauſe it to be defamed, and thoſe who are to determine, and that none joyn with ſuch a ſingular ſpirit as would lead him to be<note n="h" place="margin">This <hi>W. R.</hi> is not a little guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of, in frequently Refuſing to refer his Matters, and Acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſce in the Judgement of a free Meeting of Friends; and when he hath upon Occaſion agreed to ſuch a Meeting, he hath made it his buſineſs to Quarrel with the Judgement and Determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof, as in the Caſe of <hi>Robert Barclay,</hi> more particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obſerved hereafter: See his Back-ſlidings, and Condemning himſelf now, in that which he Allowed not formerly.</note> ſole judge in his own cauſe, but in the reſtoring and healing ſpirit of Chriſt, both the offended, and the offender may for the truths ſake ſubmit to the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God in his people, in thoſe Citys, place, or Countrys, with ſuch friends, as the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties concerned ſhall call to their Aſſiſtance.</p>
                  <p>And Friends, let the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Gods power, heavenly and peaceable Wisdom,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:52601:13"/>be Eyed in all your Aſſemblies, that the Government of the Truth and Righteouſneſs may be Exalted over All, that true Iudgement and Mercy may have the place: And although a general Care be not laid upon<note n="i" place="margin">This Teſtimony in behalf of the good Order and Government in the Church of Chriſt; and <hi>G. F.</hi> as one more particularly Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental therein, as that which Anſwered God's Witneſs in All, compared with the Character of him and it, in <hi>W. R.</hi> his Book, would require large Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; to which, we give general Reference, but may inſtance a few Paſſages in <hi>pag.</hi> 45. of the firſt part, he ſaith, We are Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous (but who that we is, he doth not ſay) the Corruption, Uſurpation, and Injuſtice may creep in by ſuch, who contend ſo much for Church-Government, with Reſpect to outward Forms of Government, ſince the Form ſome take to Govern, is in ſome Reſpect, worſe than the Forms of divers Apoſtate Chriſtians; this is a wicked Abuſe of many Faithful Friends, concerned in his Charge, in the ſaid page.</note> every Member, touching the good Order and Government in the Churches Affairs; nor hath many Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſſed therein: yet the Lord hath ſaid it more upon ſome, in whom he hath opened Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel for that End; and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly in our dear Brother, <hi>God's</hi> Faithful Labourer, <hi>G. F.</hi> for the Help of many. And God hath in His Wiſdome, afforded thoſe Helps and Governments in the Churches, which are not to be Deſpiſed, being in Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to Chriſt, the one Head, and Lawgiver, Anſwering, his Witneſs in all, and ſo all ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Counſel, Admonitions, or Teſtimonies<note n="k" place="margin">
                        <p>How doth this agree with his Advice in the Epiſtle? and, What is the matter now? Is the Conſtitution of the Government owned amongſt the People cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Quakers, and the helps af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded thereby, which he ſo much Commended formerly, as having a Service in a Subten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency to the Light, and as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from it, now become al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, or ceaſed, and worſe than the Apoſtate Chriſtians (God forbid) and Rebuke his lying Spirit? what were thoſe Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Governments that <hi>W. R.</hi> with others gave ſuch a Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon the Deſpiſers of, but the ſame he now poureth out ſo much Contempt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? And is the Encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of the People of God to be Diligent and Faithful therein, and to Judge all contrary, exalted, and oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Spirits; now become do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting on outward Orders, and a neglect of God's Teaching, as he Inſinuateth in his <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face, pag.</hi> 30. or juſtly be termed Impoſition, Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or Setting up another thing than Chriſt Jeſus, to be King and Lawgiver; no ſuch matter: It appears by this Epiſtle, he thought it not ſo formerly; or are the ſaid Helps and Governments Chriſt hath ſo afforded in his Church, as he confeſſeth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the promoting a Zealous Obſervation of other Men's Lines, made ready to their Hands; or the pretended Dictates of the Spirit, through others, or at beſt through that one Man <hi>George Fox,</hi> as is Contained in <hi>pag.</hi> 40. of his <hi>Preface.</hi> No ſure, the Change is in himſelf; ſee his Prevarication, and how he is become Degenerated, and found by his Writing and Oppoſition, pulling down and Deſtroying what he once Built up.</p>
                        <p>What is the matter that he had ſo much Unity with <hi>George Fox,</hi> and adhered to him in theſe things formerly, and now ſo bitterly Smiteth, and Inveighs againſt him? Is he <hi>(viz.) George Fox,</hi> a Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged Man? No, Thouſands can Witneſs to the contrary whoſe Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences he hath Anſwered, and doth Anſwer in the Power and Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God; and is <hi>A ſweet Savour of Chriſt in them that are Saved, and in them that Periſh:</hi> For the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>
                              <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto one, We are the ſavour of Death unto Death; and unto the other, the Savour of Life unto Life,</hi> 2 Cor. 2.15, 16. or are the principal Matters of Fact, which <hi>William Rogers</hi> alledgeth againſt him, ſaid to be of late Years, ſince he ſo nighly owned him: No, no, but many of them long before; from which, as alſo what he Chargeth him with of later Times, he hath already Anſwered, what ſeemed worth taking Notice of; and Vindicated his Innocency, and Manifeſted <hi>William Rogers</hi> his malicious Abuſes of him.</p>
                     </note> that have been given Forth, and Received in the Univerſal Spirit of Life and Vnity, have their Service for God, in ſubjection to his Light and Subſervency to, and in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to Anſwer the great Rule and Law of the Spirit of Life, as proceeding from it: And they that are Spiritual, will acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge thoſe things ſpoken or
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:52601:14"/>written from this Spirit: and for this end, to be the Requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings of the Lord; and many in divers Places have Recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Help and Encouragement from Him; through thoſe Helps and Governments, that he hath Afforded in the Church, the True and Living Body, which we are Members of; in which (as all keep their Habitations) there is a Sweetneſs, &amp; Harmony of Life, Vnity, and Subjection, one to a-another, and a preſerving one of another, in the Lord. Yet every Man in his own proper Order; for every Member of the body is
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:52601:14"/>not<note n="l" place="margin">
                        <hi>Note,</hi> it is not Intended, or Underſtood hereby, That ſome of the Members of Chriſt's Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, ſhould be without his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Light in their own inward Parts: for Chriſt the Head of the Body, is One in the Male, and in the Female (as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaith) who gives Light un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them all; which as they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide in it, gives them to ſee, and have Unity one with another, and with the Doctrine, Counſel, and Inſtruction, which he Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately opens, &amp; gives forth, in, &amp; by, his Faithful Servants, in whom he more fully o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens his Divine Counſel; unto whom, he hath committed a Diſpenſation of the Everlaſting Goſpel of Peace, who faithfully Labour in the Life and Doctrine of Chriſtianity; and therein are good inſtrumental Helps in Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</note> an Eye; and yet each Member hath its proper place, and Service, and all in Subjec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the one Life, Power, and Head, which is Chriſt; &amp; it hath been obſerved by us, that that Spirit which deſpiſeth Government and Dominion, and ſpeaks Evil of Dignities; is either a Singular, or a Self-Righteous, Self-Separating Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that would (it ſelf) bear Rule, and be Iudge over all; which alſo Works to ſtumble and darken the ſimple, or a Looſe, Diſobedient, Careleſs Spirit, that would not be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, but altogether live at Eaſe in the Fleſh, and fleſhly Liberty, which the Power of God will Rebuke;<note n="m" place="margin">It had been well for <hi>W. R.</hi> if he ever had this Dominion, that he had kept it; for it is the ſame, and no other, that the Brethren ſeek, and are Exerciſed in, for no other End or Intereſt, as they have Declared; God is their Witneſs, who knoweth the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of all Hearts, and will plead with <hi>W. R.</hi> in his Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Judgements, for being found in the wrong Spirit, that doth ſurmize or inſinuate Jealouſies, to the contrary, as theſe Lines Import.</note> but though he hath given us Dominion o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver that Spirit, and its perverſe Wayes, which oppoſeth the Power, and would work Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion, and lead into corrupt Liberty; yet 'tis no Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on over your Faith, that we ſeek, but that we may be Help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of your Ioy in the Lord; and you as diligent Co-workers, together in the Faith and Love of God, wherein we may be all a mutual Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, Ioy, and Crown of Rejoycing, one to another, as having one Maſter, and we all Brethren in Him, who is the Lord of the Houſhold, and God of Glory;
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:52601:15"/>whoſe Glorious preſence is with us; and it is a wrong Spirit that would ſurmiſe, or inſinuate Iealouſies, or beget prejudice againſt the Faithful Labourers in the Goſpel, and Helpers in Government, to Miſ-repreſent ſuch, as aiming at any other Ends and Intereſts than Chriſt's Intereſt and Government over all, which God is Record, we are clear from ſeeking or claiming at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other. And in his<note n="n" place="margin">How came <hi>W. R.</hi> by this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and Power, to give Judgement againſt ſuch Works, and Workers, and deny, and quarrel with it now? Is it not Manifeſt to be, becauſe he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf is fallen into the ſame Snare, not only of being Secret, but now as an open Enemy to the Truth, and Heavenly Society therein. And we are perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, if he Repent not, the time will come, when he will find his own Judgement, as it is already ſeen by the Faithful, to be Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified in his own particular.</note> Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Power, we ſtand Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes againſt that Spirit fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, both in our open and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Enemies, which either Smites at our Heavenly So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, or would break our Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with the Prince of Peace, who is our Head and Lawgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, unto whom Thrones, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, Principallities, and Powers are jubject, be Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for ever, unto whoſe Power and Government we commit you all, and in true, and endeared Love, Reſt</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your Dear Brethren</hi> William Rogers. Authur Eaſtmead.
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>William Penn,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>James Hall,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>George Coal,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Charles Marſhal,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>William Gibſon,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>John Moone,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>John Langſtaff,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Samuel Thornton,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Edward Brown,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>James Claypoole,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Robert Barclay,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>John Cox,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>James Merrick,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Thomas Briggs,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Morgan Watkins,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>John Rauce,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Charles Lloyd,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Richard Almond,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Robert Cary,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Thomas Green,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>John Anderdon,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Alexander Parker,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>John Whitehead,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>William Brend,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <pb n="29" facs="tcp:52601:15"/>
                           <item>
                              <hi>John Bauldren,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Will. Fallowfield,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Samuel Cater,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>James Adamſon,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Stephen Criſp,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>John Grave,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>George Whitehead,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Jaſper Batt,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Thomas Salthouſe,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Samuel Wattſon,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Luke Howard,</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>We deſire the true Copies hereof may be Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to, and Read in the ſeveral Quarterly, Monethly, and other Meetings, of Friends and Brethren throughout <hi>England,</hi> and elſewhere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if it be queried <hi>How cometh it to paſs, that</hi> William Rogers <hi>is ſo Metamorphoſed or Changed in a few Years, as to appear thus in perfect Contradiction to himſelf, in judgment about the ſame things; either he muſt be in the right then, and wrong now; or contrarywiſe, in the right now, and wrong then?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Anſwer according to the Witneſs of the Spirit of Truth in our hearts, and experience we have had of him by his late Fruits, that <hi>Evil</hi> (<hi>viz. <hi>Pride</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>Envy</hi>) hath altered his Underſtanding, and <hi>Deceit</hi> beguil'd his Soul, and <hi>Prejudice</hi> againſt the Lords Work, and many of his faithful Labourers hath Eaten as a Canker until the Love that was once raiſed in him, came to be deſtroy'd: And now his Soul is fill'd with <hi>Bitterneſs,</hi> in which the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity lodgeth, and though his pretences are high, as all his Predeceſſors in this Work were, in whom Satan was Transformed, and wrought in a Myſtery; yet with the Light he is ſeen, &amp; judged to be as they alſo were, in the <hi>My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of Iniquity:</hi> And what, though in his fallen Wiſdom, which is Accurſt, he lifts up himſelf on High, and would have the World believe, as though <hi>God had raiſed him up as the great Reformer of our Age;</hi> yet do we know, and are aſſured with many hundreds more of the Flock and Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of God in this City, and in the Counties adjacent, to whom he is perſonally known, That <hi>He is not of God;</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:52601:16"/>for, we have not only try'd his Spirit, but his Works alſo have made him manifeſt. And albeit, he begins and makes uſe of theſe Words of Chriſt in his abuſive Book <hi>(As I hear, I judg)</hi> we know he is a man Uncircumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in Heart and Ears, and therefore his judgment is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, &amp; he hath no right to take up the words of Chriſt, &amp; apply them to himſelf; for, he hath judged many he hath never heard. Chriſt ſaid, <hi>judge not according to outward Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, but judge Righteous judgment:</hi> But how void <hi>William Rogers</hi> is, either of the <hi>true hearing</hi> or <hi>judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> hath been by his Un-Chriſtian behaviour amongſt us, and by his manifold abuſes in his Book (grounded upon <hi>Reports</hi> and <hi>Conjectures</hi>) of many innocent men, and by his <hi>ſelf Contradiction,</hi> as by the foregoing <hi>Epiſtle,</hi> is abundantly manifeſt. And, truly we are ſorry for him, that he ſhould ſo backſlide, as he hath done, and fall from the right way of the Lord, and foot-ſteps of his Flock and Family, which he once rejoyced in. And it's ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry remarkable; to ſee how directly <hi>William Rogers</hi> hath troden in the ſame foot-ſteps with the ſeveral <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtates</hi> that have ariſen up from among our ſelves, in that, like <hi>Saul</hi> againſt <hi>David,</hi> he hath ſo malitiouſly le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel'd his Arrows, and caſt his <hi>Javlin</hi> againſt that one Man, <hi>G. F.</hi> above all others; loading him as hitherto hath been done with manifold <hi>Calumnies</hi> and <hi>Reproa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,</hi> which the Lord hath, and we doubt not, but ſtill will blaſt, and make his <hi>Innocency</hi> to appear over all his wicked Deſigns, to the confuſion of <hi>his,</hi> and <hi>Truths Adverſaries,</hi> whatſoever they are, or may pretend to the contrary. And, the cauſe thereof, we conclude to be from the Enmity of the <hi>wicked one,</hi> the <hi>Son of Perdition,</hi> that hath entred the heart of this man, <hi>William Rogers,</hi> as he hath other Inſtruments formerly, where he ſits, and is Exalted, in a high Profeſſion, to the end that he may the better deceive, and draw from the <hi>Bleſſed Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:52601:16"/>&amp; fellowſhip in the Truth and heavenly Guidance of the Light it ſelf,</hi> into a <hi>Selfiſh, Diſorderly, Looſs, Libertine Spirit, from God,</hi> and unſubmiſſion, &amp; unſubjection one unto another, according to the Goſpel-Order in the Churches of Chriſt; That by how much the more God hath made uſe of our dear Friend, <hi>G. F.</hi> and honoured him with the firſt Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of the Light and Truth, as reveal'd in our day and age, whereby the Hearts of many Thouſands have been gathered from the Evil of their wayes, and converted un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, and remain living Witneſſes of the Appearance, Bleſſing and Preſence of God with him, and bear the Seal of his Miniſtry, and continued faithfulneſs unto God therein, who hath alſo indued him with Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Wiſdom, in the openings of his Council, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he hath been, and is inſtrumental in the hand of the Lord; <hi>For the ſettlement of good Order and Diſcipline in the Church of Chriſt,</hi> as <hi>Helps</hi> and <hi>Governments;</hi> for its Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment and Comfort in him, who is its ſure Foundation and Rock forever. By ſo much the more abundantly, hath the Enemy wrought by his Inſtruments againſt that faithful Servant of the Lord, <hi>viz. G. F.</hi> to hinder the Lords Work, and to Obſcure his bleſſed appearance in him, and through him, and among his Choſen People, to their joy and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in their Heavenly Society, they are gathered into: But the Lord hath hitherto blaſted their Deſigns, and made their Folly manifeſt, as he doth, and is doing at this day, Bleſſed be his Name for ever.</p>
            <p>We ſhall now proceed to take ſome notice of a few more paſſages in his Book, and <hi>firſt,</hi> that, in the <hi>2d.</hi> and <hi>3d.</hi> pages of his <hi>Preface,</hi> wherein he ſaith, <hi>That ſo great a Concern of Conſcience lieth on many, to encourage the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication of his Book, as we can no longer forbear, lest it ſhould be reputed, that the Doctrine and Life of Christianity were whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly extinct amongſt the aforeſaid People.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:52601:17"/>
            <p>Here, as in divers other places of his Book, we cannot but Obſerve, that, he claims <hi>many</hi> to be concern'd in Conſcience with him, in the publiſhing thereof, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by magnifying his Number; But, who or where thoſe <hi>many</hi> are, we know not; <hi>William Rogers</hi> might (if he had pleas'd) or may yet, tell us by what Name they are call'd, and we would have him know, we expect it; that ſo, we may be able to ſatisfly our ſelves, upon a due Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of their example in Life and Doctrine, whether they are men more fitly qualified than himſelf, for ſuch an undertaking; eſpecially if any of them live in this City, becauſe upon enquiry hitherto we have not been able to find them out. It ſeems to us, if <hi>W. R.</hi> had ſo many bright, and ſhining lights in the Doctrine and Life of Chriſtianity, above the reſt of their Neighbours, <hi>(viz.)</hi> the people call'd <hi>Quakers,</hi> to whom it was become ſuch a <hi>Concern of Conſcience,</hi> as he writes, they ſhould be as a City, ſet on a hill, and come forth, and own it publickly in the face of all people: but this we are doubtful is too plain and open for him, to talk of many in the dark to father a work of darkneſs, ſeems to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry more credit with it than to particularize a few as <hi>Raſh, Self-will'd,</hi> and <hi>Injurious</hi> as himſelf, that doth own it.</p>
            <p>Alas, Alas! To what a <hi>height of Folly</hi> and <hi>Pinacle of Conceitedneſs</hi> is this man arriv'd. The <hi>Prodigy</hi> of our Age, as it ſhould ſeem by his Book and <hi>Bullwork</hi> againſt <hi>Apoſtacy,</hi> now ſhewing himſelf as an Enſign to the Nation, leſt it ſhould be reputed, <hi>that the Doctrine and Life of Chriſtianity were wholly Extinct among the People call'd Quakers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to the <hi>Life of Chriſtianity,</hi> we have already mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted how much he is a ſtranger to it, through his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe Practices among us, and corrupt Nature Ruling in him, and conſequently, a very unfit man to be ſet up as
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:52601:17"/>ſo <hi>great a Reformer,</hi> or, to concern himſelf ſo much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the miſcarriages of others, as he accounts them, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.5. <hi>Thou Hypocrite, firſt caſt out the beam out of thine own Eye, &amp; then ſhalt thou ſee clearly to caſt out the mote out of thy Brothers Eye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as to the <hi>Doctrines of Chriſtianity,</hi> not to inſiſt upon his ſaying and unſaying again, (<hi>viz.</hi> in that he hath one while confeſſed they are <hi>publikely own'd,</hi> another while charging an <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> therein, We refer to the many prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Teſtimonies written by divers eminent Brethren, ſtill living, in the Defence of the Goſpel-Truths; and how much in perſpecuity and clearneſs, they are beyond any thing in <hi>William Rogers</hi> his Book, is left to the impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Reader to judge; as a Reproof to his ſtrange conceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Confidence,</hi> as well as falſe and ungodly <hi>inſinuations</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them and the People call'd <hi>Quakers</hi> in general, as though the <hi>Doctrin and Life of Chriſtianity were in danger of being reputed to be wholly Extinct among them, unleſſe he and a few others</hi> (in compariſon of the People call'd Quakers; however he is pleaſed to magnify their number) <hi>who are of party with him, had diſcharg'd that concern of Conſcience,</hi> he pretends <hi>lay on many, to incourage the publication of his Book,</hi> deſigning thereby, no doubt, being the natural Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence of his Lynes, to obviate the Univerſality of ſuch a Reputation, by rendring themſelves the men that kept their primitive Station in the Life of Truth, and retain'd the ancient Doctrines thereof, whil'ſt they undertook ſo generally to detect ſo many of the moſt publick, and moſt reputed Quakers (ſo call'd) and their Adherents, who are People in general who have Unity with them in the Truth and bleſſed order thereof (and which makes up the other part) of Degeneracy therefrom into an <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> and <hi>Innovation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It ſtill ſeemes ſtrange to us, that ſuch men (if ſuch they be whom <hi>W. R.</hi> intends) ſhould lye ſo hidden and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal'd,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:52601:18"/>as not to be found, and no leſs ſtrange, that they ſhould make uſe of, and encourage <hi>W. R.</hi> to be their mouth to ſpeak to the world by, who hath known ſo little of the ſanctification of his Nature, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly very unlike what his lines beſpeak them to be. This adds no Credit to their matter, but gives juſt occaſion of <hi>jealouſie,</hi> and will do, unleſs they diſprove it, by a diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of themſelves, That what ever is pretended, they are but too much like him; for if it be otherwiſe, and that they really are ſuch as <hi>excel in the Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Life of Chriſtianity,</hi> let them come forth, and ſhew themſelves: What though they are but as <hi>one of a City,</hi> and <hi>two of a Tribe,</hi> yet if they have the Truth on their ſides, that is ſtronger than all, and ſhall prevail.</p>
            <p>It is likewiſe to be obſerved, after what an <hi>injurious</hi> as well as <hi>diſingenuous</hi> a rate <hi>William Rogers,</hi> hath dealt with the People call'd <hi>Quakers,</hi> in often gathering up the words of ſome perſon or perſons, we know not who, neither doth he tell us, nor when, if ever ſpoken by any, particularly the Doctrine in the ſixth <hi>page</hi> of his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face which he makes ſo much adoe about in ſeveral parts of his Book, as one of his great <hi>Marks of Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi> wherewith he reflects upon the Brethren, <hi>(viz.) Let us exclude Reaſoning, the Wiſdome, and the jealouſie, and let us have an Eye to the Brethren.</hi> But who ſeeth not the unrighteouſneſs of ſuch dealing, which together with many pieces and ſcraps of matter collected out of divers Papers and Epiſtles, he hath not only quoted in ſuch a confuſed manner, that no Reader, unleſs before acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the grounds and occaſion thereof, can rightly underſtand, and conſequently, not in a capacity to make a ſound judgment therefrom: But to extort a judgment, as it were, from the inconſiderate and prejudiced, he hath ſo paraphraſed upon ſuch Words and Doctrines, ſuch ſcraps and pieces of matter, ſo collected by him, and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:52601:18"/>framed ſuch <hi>notorious falſe inſinuations,</hi> and <hi>perverſions</hi> therefrom, and <hi>vilifications</hi> of many faithful and emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent <hi>Labourers,</hi> and through them the generallity of the People call'd <hi>Quakers</hi> that adhear to them, as guilty of ſuch things as their Souls abhor, and is particularly men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the beginning of this Treatiſe, which the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous God of Heaven and Earth ſees and beholds, and will <hi>plead with him,</hi> and recompence him for it in his due time, if he Repent not.</p>
            <p>The next thing we have to notice of, is his unjuſt Charges and Reflections on thoſe <hi>Sixty-Six</hi> Friends and Brethren, that ſubſcribed the <hi>Epiſtle</hi> dated from <hi>Ellis Hooks</hi> his Chamber, the <hi>12th.</hi> of the <hi>7th.</hi> month, 1677. and more particularly with relation to his manifeſt abuſe of the four Friends of <hi>Briſtol,</hi> that were concern'd therein.</p>
            <p>On this <hi>Epiſtle</hi> it is (to take little notice of his <hi>Objections a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Conſtitution of the Meeting</hi> it came from, more than to tell him, that what he would not have it to be, that it is, (<hi>viz.</hi> from the <hi>Yearly-Meeting</hi>) we obſerve <hi>William Rogers</hi> grounds another of his great <hi>Marks of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtacy</hi> he chargeth thoſe Brethren with, <hi>viz. judging of the Merits of the Cauſe without hearing the ſame,</hi> Preface, page the Sixth; and for proof thereof, ſaith, <hi>That</hi> John Story <hi>and</hi> John Wilkinſon <hi>have been judg'd by many of the Subſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers thereof, if not all, without a hearing of either Party; for, that the Epiſtle doth not import, that the judgment given was on the hearing either of one or both Parties, Convened before them,</hi> 2d. part <hi>page</hi> 77. But the <hi>fallaciouſneſs</hi> of this <hi>Inſinuation</hi> will eaſily appear by what follows.</p>
            <p>We have already given an Account of the <hi>Meeting,</hi> that many Friends and Brethren had with <hi>Iohn Story,</hi> and <hi>Iohn Wilkinſon</hi> at <hi>Drawell</hi> in <hi>Yorkſhire,</hi> and the Reſult of that <hi>Meeting.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We have alſo ſignified, how <hi>J. S.</hi> and <hi>J. W.</hi> have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haved
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:52601:19"/>themſelves ſince, to the grief of thoſe very Friends, abuſing them both by word and writing, with many op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probrious Terms, diſowning their Judgement, as <hi>Unjuſt,</hi> and <hi>Unrighteous,</hi> &amp;c. Extenuating <hi>Their Paper of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation,</hi> not owning it as ſuch againſt themſelves, continuing their former Subſcriptions to a Paper tending to a Separation, upheld and maintained in ſome part of <hi>Weſtmoreland,</hi> &amp;c. whereby they made void, as to themſelves, the Benefit of all thoſe Tranſactions at the Meeting aforeſaid, and which would have Succeeded, had they behaved themſelves as they ought to have done: But foraſmuch as they have continued in the ſame <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Diviſion</hi> and <hi>Separation,</hi> Contemning the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel and Advice of thoſe Brethren, they ſtill ſtand juſtly Chargeable with thoſe things they were before found Guilty of.</p>
            <p>Thoſe things conſider'd, the <hi>Sixty Six</hi> Friends and Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, who Subſcribed that <hi>Epistle,</hi> ſome of them being the ſame that were perſonally preſent, &amp; concerned at the Meeting at <hi>Drawell,</hi> before mentioned; and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther approved Travelling Brethren in the Work of the Miniſtry (however now termed, <hi>Vpuarts, Apoſtates,</hi> and <hi>Innovators</hi>) having received ſatisfactory Knowledge, upon the undoubted Credit and Teſtimony of many Brethren of their Proceedings at <hi>Drawell.</hi> And likewiſe, many of them being abundantly ſenſible; and divers having certain Knowledge of their perſiſting in the ſame. Spirit of Diviſion and Separation, had a Concern upon their Spirits, under the Apprehenſion of the dangerous Conſequence of ſuch Men's Travelling up and down in a diſreconcil'd Eſtate (ſowing, and ſpreading their Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents and Diviſions, being forewarn'd thereof) with a renewed Admonition againſt that Spirit of Diviſion, and cauſion to Friends to beware thereof, which was the cauſe of their giving forth that Teſtimony; which how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:52601:19"/>they (<hi>William Rogers,</hi> and ſome others) are Diſquie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at, is Juſt and Righteous in the Sight of God, and ſtands good upon their Heads, and will do, untill they Repent, and be humbled under the ſence of their great Offences.</p>
            <p>Friends having this Senſe, as abundantly appears in their <hi>Epiſtle,</hi> That they ſtill perſiſted in the ſame <hi>Spirit of Oppoſition and Separation,</hi> as before; What Merits of the Cauſe were here to judge of more, than was alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Determined, unleſs it were <hi>Their perſiſting in the ſame Work of ſowing and ſpreading their Diviſions, and offering their Gifts, whilſt diſreconciled to the Brethren?</hi> Which was Evident to the Friends of that Meeting, in their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting the Advice and Counſel before given them, by <hi>Epistle</hi> from the <hi>Yearly-Meeting,</hi> to the contrary.</p>
            <p>We having thus open'd the Ground of this Matter, do Commend it, with the following <hi>Queries,</hi> to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of the Impartial Reader, to Judge, Whether ſuch a Charge, as <hi>William Rogers</hi> hath given, againſt no leſs than above <hi>Sixty Friends and Brethren,</hi> at once, as no ſmall Mark of their <hi>Apoſtacy, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </hi> of being <hi>Guilty of judging the Merits of a Cauſe, without hearing the ſame,</hi> or of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owning <hi>J. S.</hi> &amp; <hi>J. W.</hi> though they could not juſtly Charge them of Evil, be rightly imputable to thoſe Brethren, upon ſigning their <hi>Epiſtle,</hi> to whom the knowledge of Matters tranſacted at <hi>Drawell,</hi> were ſo Tranſmitted, as is before Related.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> Whether? Since it was not feazible, that the Church, or every Friend concerned, for the underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the Truth of the Matter, relating to <hi>J. S.</hi> and <hi>J. W.</hi> could go down into the <hi>North,</hi> to hear the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation thereof, the Teſtimony given in a Narrative, from ſo many faithful, approved Men, upon inward Senſe, and plain external Evidences of Witneſſes, be not ſufficient proof againſt the ſaid Men?</item>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:52601:20"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> And if this be not, What can be? Matters conſidered, with thoſe Circumſtances aboveſaid, amongſt the Societies and Tranſactions of Men, either in things Temporal or Spiritual, wherein Men many times tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act Matters upon the unqueſtioned Credit one of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, whilſt under neceſſity of great Remoteneſs one from another?</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Whether to give Credit to one or two Men, in his or their own Cauſe, againſt more than twenty Eye and Ear Witneſſes, who are Conſcientiouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned to hear and ſearch into the Truth of Matters, be conſiſtent with Reaſon, Chriſtianity, and true Wiſdom?</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Whether not only the Refuſal of ſuch Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony, Evidence, and Judgement, as was given from the Meeting at <hi>Drawell,</hi> upon Examination, and Proof of Matters, <hi>John Story</hi> and <hi>John Wilkinſon</hi> being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, but the Invalidating thereof, and Reflecting on thoſe Meetings and Friends (as <hi>Falſe Accuſers, and Judges of the Merits of a Cauſe, before they Hear it</hi>) who do Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it, and joyn with it, and unto whom the Truth hath been ſo evidently Tranſmitted, carrieth not with it an unavoidable Tendency to over-throw the <hi>Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Credit, Service,</hi> and <hi>frequent Practice of Friends of Truth, in their Meetings throughout the Nation,</hi> in any Caſe; and thereby to Strengthen the Hand of Tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, and their Abettors in their Inſolency againſt the Truth, and the Friends thereof in General?</item>
            </list>
            <p>Let all Perſons of Sobriety Judge, Whether the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence of this, which hath been, and is <hi>William Rogers's</hi> Practiſe, be not to open a wide Door for <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtacy and Licentiouſneſs,</hi> by which means, <hi>A Man may be proved <hi>The Worſt of Men in one Country,</hi> and come into another, and stand upon his <hi>Iuſtification,</hi> and be <hi>Abetted</hi> therein, notwithſtanding the Testimony of ſuch as heard Matters prov'd against him?</hi> And, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:52601:20"/>this doth not Manifeſtly De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Credit</hi> one of another, the Ground, both of Chriſtian and Civil Society.<note n="*" place="margin">Had not that, the Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of this, had it been the Practice of the People called <hi>Quakers,</hi> as it Manifeſtly hath been of <hi>W. R.</hi> and his party, given the World juſt Cauſe to Judge, as <hi>W. R.</hi> by many <hi>Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions,</hi> and falſe <hi>Premiſes</hi> doth inſinuate, <hi>That the Doctrine and Life of Chriſtianity, were in danger to be wholly Exſtinct amongſt them.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>And now, as to <hi>William Rogers</hi> his ſeveral Charges a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Four Friends of <hi>Briſtol,</hi>
               </hi> of being <hi>Falſe Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers, and refuſing to admit a Meeting to Prove the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in Charge, in the aforementioned Epiſtle againſt</hi> John Story <hi>and</hi> John Wilkinſon, <hi>before an equal number of Friends, Choſen on each Part,</hi> part 2. pag. 10.</p>
            <p>To this we Anſwer, It's no wonder <hi>William Rogers</hi> hath termed thoſe friends <hi>Falſe Accuſers,</hi> ſeeing he hath not ſtuck to ſay the like, or worſe, concerning many other <hi>Faithful Brethren.</hi> How Unrighteous this Charge is againſt the <hi>Four Friends of Briſtol,</hi> or any of the reſt that Signed the <hi>Epiſtle,</hi> may appear by what is already Written: Neither do they nor we remember, <hi>That e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver we refuſed a Meeting upon thoſe Terms, provided, they ſhould agree, what ſhould be taken for Evidence;</hi> although, if they had refuſed ſuch a Meeting, we cannot ſee how that could deſerve any juſt Reflection, ſeeing Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence teacheth us; <hi>That when the Guilty, or any of party for them, hath equal Liberty to chuſe, without whoſe Concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, no diciſive Judgement muſt be given: The Conſequence thereof, is like to effect nothing but Controverſy, and a ſhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the Offender,</hi> as is before hinted, which Leadeth us to make this <hi>Query;</hi> That</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whether the admitting of no Meeting to be equal for the deciſion of ſpiritual matters in Controverſy, but what is made up of a certain number of choſen men of each ſide to judge (the offender having an equal Choice)
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:52601:21"/>be not wrong and inconſiſtent with the practice of the Friends of Truth; and hath not a tendency to make void the Authority of our Meetings, in which the Power of the Lord, in its free Exerciſe, is to be Guide and Iudge?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, whatever <hi>William Rogers</hi> pretends, The <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction to a Meeting by conſent,</hi> principally lay in the <hi>diſagreement,</hi> as to the reflection of this Queſtion, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What ſhould be ſufficient Evidence for proof of thoſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Charges contained in the Epistle?</hi> which lead the four Friends, and others in their behalf, to inſiſt upon the <hi>Narrative of Friends from <hi>Drawell,</hi>
               </hi> with the <hi>Examinations and proofs of matters there,</hi> which they had in Cuſtody, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with <hi>John Story</hi> and <hi>John Wilknſons Writings,</hi> to which their hands were; but this would not be accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of by <hi>W. R.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And, as to the other abuſive paſſage in the ſame page of his Book, <hi>viz. Whether will they</hi> (meaning the four Friends of <hi>Briſtol</hi>) <hi>as yet admit a Hearing before any Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, wherein the Witneſſes to the Accuſations, ſhould be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded from being judges.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Both they and we ſay, Its utterly falſe; moſt of us then, being preſent at the Meeting, which was on the <hi>16th.</hi> day of the <hi>5th.</hi> month, 1677. where theſe things were diſcourſed, do declare, that we never heard them ſo expreſs themſelves, but do look upon it as one of <hi>William Rogers</hi>'s ungodly Charges, and grievous Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſions of their words; what was ſpoken, from whence it is ſuppoſed <hi>William Rogers</hi> hath falſly drawn the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-mentioned Concluſion, was, <hi>That they could not have any of the ſeveral Brethren excluded from being preſent, and to be concern'd in judgment, that had given forth the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count from <hi>Drawell</hi>
               </hi> (whom <hi>William Rogers</hi> indeed hath call'd <hi>falſe Accuſers</hi>) <hi>but who were faithful Witneſſes to the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:52601:21"/>proof of the Accuſations, and not Accuſers themſelves,</hi> as his Charge ſeems to inſinuate: All which things they have manifeſted more at large, in a partiular Anſwer long ſince. And although, <hi>William Rogers</hi> is pleaſed to ſay, in his Book, <hi>That a Reply thereto hath manifeſted their <hi>noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Weakneſs,</hi> if Charity may excuſe them from <hi>wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Wickedneſs;</hi>
               </hi> But how, nor wherein, neither they, nor we know. As for his expreſſion of <hi>notorious Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> we eſteem it as the Fruit of an over-fond conceit of his own Abillities, above others: And if he hath Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to excuſe thoſe Friends from the Imputation of wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Wickedneſs, we ſhould be glad of the like, were not our Eyes and Ears witneſſes of ſuch Fruits from him, on di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers occaſions, as almoſt leaves us void of room, or any juſt pretence for ſo much <hi>Charity,</hi> in many reſpects, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him.</p>
            <p>And as for the <hi>Briſtol Certificate,</hi> ſubſcribed by <hi>twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſeven Friends</hi> on behalf of <hi>G. F.</hi> his Innocency, to the beſt of their knowledge <hi>As a man remote in Spirit and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, from any ſuch Practice, either in <hi>Briſtol</hi> or elſe where, as <hi>Flying in times of Perſecution,</hi> though often charged therewith by <hi>Apoſtates</hi> and bad <hi>Spirits,</hi> and now imply'd in</hi> William Rogers<hi>'s Charge against him:</hi> To which they not only oppoſe their Obſervation of him in <hi>Briſtol,</hi> but their Experience, and confirmed ſince to the contrary, by his large <hi>Travells, Sufferings,</hi> and <hi>Impriſonments</hi> in many <hi>Iales,</hi> in which <hi>They never knew that he hath flinch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but endured patiently,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Which Teſtimony of thoſe Friends of <hi>Briſtol</hi> ſtands clear, and unſpotted over all <hi>W. R.</hi> his Cavils, and inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Reflections in the <hi>69th.</hi> and <hi>70th. pages</hi> of his fifth part, wherein he compares them to <hi>Perjured Iuformers,</hi> ſuggeſting, <hi>That their Evidence muſt needs be falſe,</hi> as though they undertook to prove a Negative, which was impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for them to do, becauſe they conjectured the time
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:52601:22"/>of <hi>G. F.'s</hi> being in <hi>Briſtol,</hi> then about fifteen years paſt (being a time of Perſecution) to which they ſuppoſed it muſt needs be, that <hi>W. R.</hi> ſhould Aſſign that fact of <hi>G. F.</hi> his departing out of the Meeting, and going down a back pair of ſtairs, to avoid the Perſecutors, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thereto, <hi>That they never knew, or could remember, any ſuch thing by him;</hi> They being generally all, or the moſt part of them, at all the Meetings <hi>G. F.</hi> was at here, and yet they do not limit or reſtrain their Teſtimony to <hi>that time only;</hi> but extend it to <hi>all others,</hi> to the beſt of their knowledge, <hi>having never ſeen any juſt occaſion for ſuch a Charge:</hi> But <hi>William Rogers</hi> taking advantage in that he had not nominated any time for his Charge, maketh uſe thereof, endeavouring thereby to baffle their Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, though in truth it renders his the weaker; hence it is, that he chargeth them with <hi>Undertaking to prove what was impoſſible for them to do, unleſs they had been at all the Mettings in <hi>Briſtol</hi> with</hi> G. F. <hi>that ever he was at with him,</hi> which is not unlikely, but that moſt of them might: But what juggling is here? and how doth this man fence and dodge, not only to extenuate the Credit of thoſe Friends Teſtimony, but to ſtave off the impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of a <hi>falſe Accuſation</hi> from himſelf, in ſaying, <hi>he had affix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed no time;</hi> and yet doth not deny, but that the time they mention, was the time intended by him, which ſhould in reaſon render their Teſtimony of more Credit with the Conſiderate.</p>
            <p>Neither doth he ſay any thing to the <hi>Objection</hi> made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his mentioning a <hi>back pair of Stairs that</hi> G. F. <hi>ſhould go down, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </hi> for indeed there was none ſuch, both pair of ſtairs being equally publick, and common for Friends conſtantly to go up and down at, out or into the ſtreet, as he and others well knew. More might be ſaid, but this we judge ſufficient to every impartial Reader, who ſhall have the ſight of that Certificate on behalf of <hi>G. F.</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:52601:22"/>and <hi>William Rogers</hi>'s <hi>Objections</hi> thereto, to manifeſt how unrighteouſly he hath done, by comparing the <hi>Subſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi> thereof to <hi>Perjured Informers,</hi> who are many of them both men and women, anciently and publickly known in this City, &amp; approved for their Truth and Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs in the Conſciences of honeſt People of all ſorts therein; The Conſideration as well as knowledge where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of in <hi>W. R.</hi> we cannot but apprehend was the Cauſe why he omitted all their Names, except One, <hi>viz <hi>Iohn Ware,</hi>
               </hi> a man leſs publickly known in the City, then moſt, if not any one of the reſt, whereby his diſingenuity and unfaithfulneſs doth not a little appear.</p>
            <p>Thus it may be ſeen, how <hi>William Rogers</hi> takes upon him to abuſe the People call'd <hi>Quakers</hi> by whole-ſale (as we uſe to ſay) having ſo learnt the habit of impudence, as ſomtimes upon his bare <hi>ſingle Credit</hi> or <hi>ſay ſo,</hi> and that in his own Cauſe too, not only to oppoſe the Truth of the Teſtimony of many Brethren; but to abuſe them with approbrious Reflections, whom he hath therefore termed <hi>falſe Accuſers</hi> and <hi>Perſecutors,</hi> and no leſs than above <hi>ſixty</hi> Friends and Brethren at once, whom he renders <hi>Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtarts, Apoſtates,</hi> and <hi>Innovators,</hi> for ſigning the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Epiſtle.</p>
            <p>And at another time, <hi>Charles Marſhall</hi> and <hi>thirty ſix Brethren</hi> more, are by him, as ſole judge in his own Cauſe, charged of being guilty of <hi>ſigning an unrighteous Paper,</hi> becauſe of their deciſive judgment given againſt him there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, upon a free hearing of the Difference betwixt <hi>him</hi> and <hi>Robert Barclay,</hi> as may be more particularly taken notice of ere we have done.</p>
            <p>And many of the Ancient and faithful Friends, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of the City of <hi>Briſtol,</hi> are wickedly compared by him to <hi>Perjured Informers,</hi> becauſe of their Chriſtian Teſtimony in behalf of <hi>G. F</hi>'s Innocency, in that matter <hi>W. R.</hi> Chargeth him with, and againſt whom his Enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:52601:23"/>and Rage is great. But let him conſider, that the time haſtneth, that <hi>for all theſe things he muſt come to judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now as to the many &amp; perſonal Injuries, &amp; Miſre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentations of <hi>Robert Barclay,</hi> and <hi>George Fox,</hi> the one with reſpect to Doctrine, the other to <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> wherewith great part of <hi>William Rogers</hi>'s Book is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd, we refer to their own, or ſome other hand, for par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Replies thereto; only noting firſt, as to the buſineſs of <hi>Robert Barclay,</hi> that it is an Argument to us of no ſmall Impudence in <hi>William Rogers,</hi> to continue his Cavils againſt His own meanings, and miſconſtructions of <hi>Robert Barclay</hi>'s Doctrin in his Book intituled, <hi>The Anarchy of the Ranters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </hi> and perfectly ſavors of his being led, and Acted by a Spirit that will be <hi>ſole judge in his own Cauſe,</hi> a thing he hath formerly Condemn'd in others, as may appear in the afore-recited Epiſtle, to which his Name was: And the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of this Obſervation is, becauſe his Unchriſtian dealing with <hi>Robert Barclay,</hi> and ſlender ground he had for his large Objections againſt ſome paſſages in his Book, was ſo clearly Evidenced in the Conſciences of many weighty Friends at <hi>London,</hi> with whom he had a Meeting by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent (<hi>Robert Barclay</hi> being preſent) for the hearing, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving his Objections, which was effectually done, and by his own Confeſſion he moſt Chriſtianly dealt with therein, &amp; the <hi>Truths</hi> aſſerted by <hi>Robert Barclay,</hi> were vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated and cleared, from the <hi>Miſconſtructions</hi> of <hi>William Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers,</hi> whereof ſome of us were both Eye and Ear Witneſſes, as at large appears, as well by the Teſtimony of that Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſubſcribed by <hi>thirty ſeven Brethren,</hi> as from <hi>VVilliam Rogers</hi> his <hi>Letter</hi> under his own hand-writing, which he drew up as ſatisfaction for the wrong he had done <hi>Robert Barclay;</hi> wherein <hi>William Rogers</hi> doth not only acknowledge, <hi>That he hath not done according to Goſpel order by</hi> Robert Barclay, <hi>but was juſtly worthy of blame, in what
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:52601:23"/>he did; But alſo, that he is perſwaded, that</hi> Robert Barclay <hi>is not principled as he and ſome others, by ſome paſſages in his Book, took him to be.</hi> Notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all this, <hi>William Rogers</hi> hath gone about in his Book, to <hi>undo,</hi> or <hi>unſay,</hi> what he hath ſaid in his <hi>Letter,</hi> and to publiſh his <hi>Objections</hi> againſt his own <hi>meanings</hi> and <hi>miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtructions</hi> of what <hi>Robert Barclay</hi> hath written in his ſaid Book, like a man fighting with his own ſhadow; thereby making void as much as in him lieth, the deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of that Meeting, reflecting on the Friends, as guilty of <hi>ſigning an Unrighteous Paper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What ſhall we ſay, or think concerning this Man, whom nothing will ſerve, but to be <hi>ſole Iudge</hi> and <hi>Vmpire</hi> in his own Cauſe; and unleſs this be granted him, he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to us reſolved to be <hi>Contentious,</hi> though it be to his own Ruin.</p>
            <p>The other thing we have to take notice of, with Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to <hi>VVilliam Rogers</hi>'s Charges againſt <hi>G. F.</hi> is (not only conſidering <hi>VVilliam Rogers,</hi> a man of ſuch a Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per as is before implyed) to hear how little reaſon <hi>G. F.</hi> had to take notice of his <hi>pretended Diſſatisfactions</hi> againſt him, though indeed <hi>reſtleſneſs, turmoile</hi> and <hi>enmity, of Spirit</hi> againſt him, manifeſt by his <hi>rude</hi> and <hi>un-chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian method</hi> he hath taken, too large here to recite; but alſo as a Reproof to his falſe Inſinuations againſt <hi>G. F.</hi> in his Book, as though <hi>he ſhunned the Test,</hi> and <hi>as being unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to ſubmit to juſtice;</hi> to manifeſt the contrary, how <hi>G. F.</hi> called <hi>William Rogers</hi> to account at a Meeting here in <hi>Briſtol,</hi> for proof of divers <hi>Charges</hi> and <hi>Inſinuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> contain'd in a Letter under <hi>William Rogers</hi> his own hand againſt him, and now made publick in <hi>William Rogers</hi> his Book, and what the Reſult of the Meeting was, as it appears by the following Certificate.</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:52601:24"/>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="certificate">
                        <p>
                           <hi>VVE under-written, being at a Meeting at</hi> Richard Sneads, <hi>the <hi>15th.</hi> of the <hi>12th.</hi> month</hi> 1677. <hi>to hear a Letter read, that was writ by</hi> William Rogers <hi>to</hi> G. F. <hi>containing ſeveral</hi> Accuſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Charges, <hi>and</hi> Inſinuations <hi>againſt him, do hereby de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, that it was read, and that</hi> William Rogers <hi>own'd it, and when he was call'd upon by</hi> G. F. William Penn, George Whitehead, Lawrence Steel, William Gibſon, <hi>and others, to prove his Accuſations and Charges againſt</hi> G. F. <hi>and others, he refuſed ſo to do; and notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he was intreated, and urged long thereto, yet ſaid,</hi> it ſhall not be, I will not proceed, unleſs <hi>G. F.</hi> will under his hand Charge me, and give me his Charge in Writing. <hi>Thus he ſhuffled with the Meeting: And though we told him, that the</hi> Letter <hi>was his, and conſequently, the</hi> Accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions <hi>and</hi> Charges <hi>were his, and therefore, that it lay at his Door to prove them, yet he perſiſted Obſtinately to give us no Proof, and ſo went his way.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>
                              <list>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>William Penn,</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Charles Jones,</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>John Moone,</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Richard Snead,</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Richard Vickris,</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>James Merrick,</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Charles Jones,</hi> Jun.</item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Peter Walter,</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Stephen Smith,</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Eraſmus Dole,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
                              </list>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Theſe things conſider'd, and <hi>William Rogers</hi> his apparent ſhifting and ſhuffling herein Manifeſted: What Reaſon had <hi>G. F.</hi> or any other, to take any more Notice of his <hi>Letters,</hi> than of <hi>Waſte-Paper?</hi> or to Regard his impertinent Rambling, Clamours, and Railing up and down in divers Parts of the Nation, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him (about Matters whereof he had already Clear'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in Writing) and that whilſt <hi>G. F.</hi> was far remote in the <hi>North;</hi> and yet when he was near the City of <hi>London,</hi> and <hi>William Rogers</hi> in the City, he would not, (as we are credibly inform'd) go to him. We ſay, What Reaſon had <hi>G. F.</hi>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:52601:24"/>or others, to Regard <hi>William Rogers</hi> in theſe practices, any more than they would any other <hi>Apoſtates</hi> or open <hi>Adverſaries?</hi> What hopes could <hi>G. F.</hi> or any other, have to ſatisfy ſuch a Man, whoſe <hi>Prejudice</hi> and <hi>Enmity</hi> was ſo great, that he was in Travel to give Vent thereto; and yet thus Manifeſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priv'd of common Modeſty and Equity, uſual amongſt Men, in caſe of Difference; inſomuch, that he either will not Acquieſce in the Determination of a Matter, when Heard and given Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon; but inſtead thereof, make it his buſineſs to inlarge his Abuſes againſt the concern'd therein; or otherwiſe ſhift and ſhuffle, and at length, utterly refuſe to make proof of his Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, when call'd thereunto?</p>
            <p>There is one thing more, we cannot omit to make men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of, <hi>viz.</hi> the manner of <hi>William Rogers</hi> his abuſive Inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Charges, not only againſt many Eminent and Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Brethren; but (through them) againſt the generality of the People call'd <hi>Quakers,</hi> as <hi>Apoſtatized,</hi> &amp;c. chiefly with Reſpect to the bleſſed <hi>Order and Government</hi> they are Exerciſed in, and is Eſtabliſhed among them, <hi>viz.</hi> That it is moſt frequently to be obſerv'd in his Book, that his Method is to draw poſitive, and ſcandalous Concluſions, and wicked Perverſions, from not only uncertain, but moſt falſe Premiſes and Conjectures, ſalving him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, as well as he can, with theſe and ſuch like Expreſſions (which are his uſual beſt Reaſons for his many foul Accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions againſt them) <hi>viz. If Reports be true, we take it to be thus; we have cauſe to Believe; I cannot but be full of Jealouſies,</hi> &amp;c. like the wicked, that ſaid, <hi>Report, and we will Report;</hi> And af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Example of <hi>Thomas Hicks,</hi> and <hi>John Faldo;</hi> when by his <hi>Suppoſitions, Jealouſies, Doubts, Reports, Meanings, and Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtructions,</hi> he hath made up his <hi>Man of Straw,</hi> as we may Term it, or <hi>Apoſtate-Innovator,</hi> and call'd him a <hi>Quaker,</hi> he then beſtirs himſelf, and as yet retaining ſome Notions of Truth in his Head, he doth bring them forth as Arguments to Fence with againſt his own Work, whilſt the Enemy of his Soul keeps him in Blindneſs, that he cannot ſee himſelf to be the Man. How much this is his manifeſt Practice throughout his whole Book, and how wretchedly bad ſuch Courſes are, is left to the impartial Reader to judge.</p>
            <p>We having thus (for the Truth's ſake) diſcovered <hi>William Rogers</hi> his <hi>Spirit</hi> and <hi>Behaviour</hi> amongſt us, and ſomething of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:52601:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>his many Abuſes in his Book, more particularly with Relation to ſome Friends, and Paſſages in this City; we Commend what we have Written to the Witneſs of God in every Conſcience, not doubting, but the judicious Reader, when he hath duely weighed the <hi>Management</hi> of <hi>William Rogers,</hi> with reference to the Matters herein treated of, will ſee Cauſe, as well from the Matters themſelves, as the ſlenderneſs of the Credit, wherewith the Abuſes therein manifeſted are attended, both to deteſt and loath ſuch extravagant Courſes as he hath taken, to Reproach the People call'd <hi>Quakers,</hi> and their <hi>Holy Profeſſion,</hi> and to ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend his Belief of other things deliver'd in his Book, againſt ſome particulars, no leſs Injurious, until time, by ſome other Hands ſo Manifeſt them.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Richard Snead,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Charles Harford,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Richard Vickris,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Charles Jones,</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Bringhurſt,</hi> Printer and Bookſeller, at the Sign of the <hi>Book</hi> in <hi>Grace-Church-Street,</hi> near <hi>Cornhil,</hi> 1681.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:52601:25"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
